HELP FOR CUSTOM WORD ANNOTATION FEATURE OF WAKAN 1.70+
======================================================

0. Overview

Wakan 1.70 introduces a new feature - the ability to read special "annotation"
files that can make Wakan display a webpage, picture or text whenever you 
display a specific word inside the Dictionary or select a specific character
in Character mode. For example, when typing word "bara" (a rose in Japanese) to
the Dictionary, Wakan can display a picture of a rose.

1. .ANO files

The annotation files are normal text files which you can create in any text
editor. They can be either plain-text (8-bit) or Unicode UCS2 (16-bit), but
I strongly recommend that you create them in Unicode UCS2 encoding. The files
must have the extension ".ANO" and must be stored in Wakan folder.

The .ANO file can contain any number of "annotation commands" - one command on
each line. The format of the annotation command is as follows:

<tag>:<annotation>

Where <tag> is specifying for what word of character the annotation should be
displayed and <annotation> is giving details about the annotation.

2. Tags

<tag> can be one of these:

a) "U"+Unicode hex code of the character-to-be-annotated (ex. "U4E00") 
b) character-to-be-annotated (only in Unicode files) (ex. "乾") 
c) written form of the word-to-be-annotated (only in Unicode files) (ex. "産業") 
d) phonetic form of the word-to-be-annotated (only in Unicode files) (ex. "さんぎょう") 
e) romanized phonetic form of the word-to-be-annotated (ex. "sangyou")
f) written form followed by phonetic form separated by "+" sign of the 
word-to-be-annotated (only in UCS2 files) - this is to prevent ambiguities 
caused by common written or phonetic form (ex. "橋+はし")

3. Annotations

<annotation> can contain several specific commands to be performed on word
or character specified by <tag>.

The format of <annotation> is: 
<command>:<parameter>,<command>:<parameter>, ...

Possibilities for <command> are:

"T" - show the text in <parameter> on word description line (for words only)
"C" - show the character/word in given foreground color 
"I" - show the image whose location is given in <parameter> in special 
"media" window 
"W" - show the webpage whose URL is given in <parameter> in special "media" 
window (specify the URL without "http://" part)

4. Compilation process

To speed up working with annotations, Wakan automatically compiles .ANO files
into a binary package file ANNOTATE.PKG. This file is recreated automatically
whenever Wakan finds a new .ANO file in its folder or it detects change in
any of the existing .ANO files. If you want to force the recompilation process,
just delete ANNOTATE.PKG and Wakan will recompile it upon startup.

5.