This file is used in testing ruby parsing routines. rubytext.txt and norubytext.txt must be identical except valid ruby is removed in the latter. Line count and numbers are important. When changing, update WakanTextTests accordingly.
学校から帰宅すると、妹がリビングで電話をしているところだった。
妹の名前は、高坂桐乃。現在十四歳。近所の中学校に通っている女子中学生だ。
中学生だ。
latin textだ。
だ。(Empty base text)
近所のだ。(Empty explicit base text)
Ruby just before the end of the line:
中学生
中学生
blah
中学生ちゅうがくせい
<ruby tag>
中学生<ruby tag inside the string>ちゅうがくせい
近所の［ruby comment］中学校に通っている女子
［ruby comment on it's own line］
中学生ちゅうがくせい
Broken Ruby elements which shouldn't be parsed:
近所》きん》じょ《きん《じょ｜中学生《《｜がくせい