This file is used in testing ruby parsing routines. rubytext.txt and norubytext.txt must be identical except valid ruby is removed in the latter. Line count and numbers are important. When changing, update WakanTextTests accordingly.
学校《がっこう》から帰宅《きたく》すると、妹《いもうと》がリビングで電話《でんわ》をしているところだった。
妹《いもうと》の名前《なまえ》は、高《こう》｜坂《さか》｜桐《きり》｜乃《の》。現在《げんざい》｜十四《じゅうし》｜歳《さい》。近所《きんじょ》の中学校《ちゅうがっこう》に通《つう》っている女子《じょし》｜中学生《ちゅうがくせい》だ。
中学生《latin text》だ。
latin text《ちゅうがくせい》だ。
《ちゅうがくせい》だ。(Empty base text)
近所の｜《ちゅうがくせい》だ。(Empty explicit base text)
Ruby just before the end of the line:
中学生《ちゅうがくせい》
中学生《ちゅうがくせ》
blah
中学生ちゅうがくせい
<ruby tag>
中学生<ruby tag inside the string>ちゅうがくせい
近所《きんじょ》の［ruby comment］中学校《ちゅうがっこう》に通《つう》っている女子《じょし》
［ruby comment on it's own line］
中学生ちゅうがくせい
Broken Ruby elements which shouldn't be parsed:
近所》きん》じょ《きん《じょ｜中学生《《｜がくせい